Hi, my name is Trevor Smith.
and in this video, I'm gonna be talking
about compilers and interpreters.
In order to understand compilers and interpreters,
I'm first gonna take you through what high level
languages and what low level languages are.
So a high level language is a language
that we can read and we can understand,
examples of high level language could be
Python, Java, C sharp, you know, the kind
of programs which we use on a regular basis.
We can actually type them
without too much thought.
and as long as we understand the functions
and the, the code itself, we have no real
issues with it and other people should be
able to read it as well, even if they don't
have a high understanding of the language.
Now, examples of low level
language falls into two areas.
One particular areas called assembly language
and this is an example of assembly language.
As you can see if you had some instruction
or some idea what was going on in there, you
probably could read it but for the average
user, they're just not gonna, they're gonna
struggle with this particular language.
So they do have their purposes and
understanding them is more difficult
than say a high level language.
And then there is machine code.
Machine code is almost impossible for us to read.
Yes, we can see ones and zeros, we can read
those machine code is written for machines.
The very machine that is actually
written for is the processor.
As you can see, this is an image of a processor.
A processor can understand ones
and zeros they understand binary.
And that's what they're built for
they're built to work with binary.
So that is pretty much what high
level and low level languages are.
Now, when we work with a compiler
or an interpreter, what we are doing
is we are converting high level
language to low level language.
Okay, so what is a compiler?
So it translates the entire program from source,
which is high level language into machine code.
So it takes your entire code and
packages it into a file or a multitude
of files, which it then can run directly.
It does produce an executable file, this is often
an exe file and that's the one that you tend to
run, but there are some advantages with compiling.
One of them is that the code is fast to produce.
Source code remains hidden, so cannot be modified
by the customer because it's compiled, it's almost
impossible to modify the actual file itself you
would have to go back to source, back to the
high level language that you were working with.
Once it's compiled, it doesn't need a
translator it solely it solely works through
your operating system, but there are some
disadvantages that come with compilers.
Compilers use a lot of computer resource,
it has to be loaded into the computer's
memory at the same time as the source
code, so you can imagine you've got your
compiler and you've got your source code.
They've got to be both in
your memory at the same time.
You do need a lot of memory in
your computer to compile a program.
If you don't, you might not have
sufficient memory and this could cause you
problems, especially for large projects.
It's also difficult to pinpoint errors
at the source without accessing the
original program before being compiled.
So if you've got a problem with your
exe file, you'll need to go back to the
pre-compiled file, the high level language,
in order to work out, what's gone wrong.
So what's an interpreter?
Well, interpreters translate each instruction,
which is taken in turn and translated into
machine code, the instruction is then executed
before the next instruction is translated.
Well, there are some advantages
with the interpreter.
Error messages are output as soon as an error
is encountered so it's easy to beat debug.
If it's reading line by line and executing each
line individually, when it encounters a problem,
it'll notify you which line is causing the
problem, it's useful for prototypes as the program
will run even when part of it has errors, it will
operate and function independent to any problems
that may be within the rest of the program.
There are some disadvantages to using an
interpreter, the execution of the program is
slow compared to that of a compiled program,
so it's reading line by line and passing
that information through an interpreter.
Instructions inside a loop have to be translated
each time the loop is entered, so if you've
got a massive loop, those instructions
are gonna continue to loop as well as the
loop itself, this is quite inefficient.
Now what I'm going to do is I'm going
to take you through a few examples so
that you understand what's going on.
So I'm gonna show you some examples in Python,
and I'm gonna show you some examples in C sharp.